The critics are raving... the natives are
restless... and the laughter is non-stop!
The Gods Must Be Crazy is a action, comedy film directed by Jamie Uys.
A Coca-Cola bottle dropped from an airplane raises havoc among a normally peaceful
tribe of African bushmen who believe it to be a utensil of the gods.
Andrew Steyn, played by Marius Weyers.
Kate Thompson, played by Sandra Prinsloo.
Xi, played by N!xau.
Sam Boga, played by Louw Verwey.
Mpudi, played by Michael Thys.
Jack Hind, played by Nic De Jager.
The Gods Must Be Crazy is a 1980 black comedy film written,
produced, edited and directed by Jamie Uys.
An international co-production of South Africa and Botswana, it is
the first film in The Gods Must Be Crazy series.
Set in Southern Africa, the film stars Namibian San farmer Nǃxau ǂToma as Xi, a hunter-gatherer of the Kalahari Desert whose
tribe discovers a glass Coca-Cola bottle dropped from an aeroplane, and believe it to be a gift from their gods.
When Xi sets out to return the bottle to the gods, his journey becomes intertwined with that of a biologist (Marius
Weyers), a newly hired village school teacher (Sandra Prinsloo), and a band of guerrilla terrorists.
The Gods Must Be Crazy was released in South Africa on September 10, 1980, by Ster-Kinekor Films, and broke several box office
records in the country, becoming the most financially successful South African film ever produced at the time.
The film was a commercial and critical success in most other countries, but took longer to find success in the United States, where it
was eventually re-released in 1984 by 20th Century Fox, with its original Afrikaans dialogue being dubbed into English.
Despite its success, the film attracted criticism for its depiction of race and
perceived ignorance of discrimination and apartheid in South Africa.
In 1989, it was followed by a sequel The Gods Must Be Crazy II.
There were also three unofficial sequels produced in
Hong Kong where Nǃxau reprised his role.
The film explores themes of airplane, africa, tribe, botswana, god.
The tone is lighthearted.